Department of Special Collections, Hesburgh Libraries of Notre Dame
American Colonial Currency Collection
[bulk: 1700-1800]
COL
University of Notre Dame Hesburgh Libraries, Department of Special Collections. 102 Hesburgh Library, Notre Dame, IN 46556
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Restrictions
The Inquisition collection is described by Louis Jordan as materials are acquired.
Acquisition and Processing Note
- Connecticut Currency March 1, 1780New London, ConnecticutConnecticutMarch 1, 1780, CT 03/01/80; Timothy Green; Seth Geen
  An emission of ฃ40,000 in bills of credit as Treasury Notes payable by March 1, 1784 with 5% interest in Spanish milled dollars at the rate of 6s per milled dollar, or silver or gold coin equivalent. Printed in New London by Timothy Green II with engraved borders and typeset text. (This Green is the first cousin once removed of Timothy Green Jr., who had printed currency for Connecticut until his death on October 3, 1763). The front of each note shows the seal of the colony with three grape vines and a hand that points to the right on some denominations and to the left on others. The scroll carries the abbreviated motto "QUI TRAN SUST" sometimes lacking the final N or final T (What is transplanted survives). In the border is: "SIGILLUM: COLON: CONNECTICENSIS" (Seal of the Colony of Connecticut). This form of the seal was on every emission from 1755 -1780. The March 1780 emission was signed and numbered in red ink and usually slash or hole canceled upon redemption. The denominations printed were: 9d, 1s3d, 1s6d, 5s, 10s, 20s and 40s notes.
  American Colonial
  - Five Shillings3458 3458, 1; John Chester, Jabez Hamlin.; Size: 88 x 71mm (front border design 86 x 69mm; back border design 51 x 65mm).
    The hand on the state seal points to the left. Hole cancel. The partially missing text from the front read as follows: "... coin equivalent, with Interest at five/ per Cent. per Annum, by the first/ Day of March, A.D. 1784./ Dated at Hart-/ ford, the first day/ of March, A.D./ 1780." The partially missing text from the back read: "Five Shillings/ Lawful Money / NEW. LONDON: / Printed by / TIMO. GREEN. 1780."
    12 o'clock (page turn)
    The Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Collection.
  - Forty Shillings Counterfeit568 568, 3; Jabez Hamlin, Elisha Williams. (both are forgeries); 88 x 70mm (front border design 85 x 69mm; back border design 54 x 67mm)
    The hand on the state seal points to the left. There is a X across the front of this counterfeit note to cancel it out. According to Newman the letter r in March and in Hartford are in their correct normal size in the counterfeit while in legal issue bills this letter is too large. Winged cherib heads are found on the design on the back.
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 lot 422. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Two Shillings, Six Pence6075 6075, 487; Signers: Benj. Payne, George Wyllys
    The hand on the state seal points to the left. Hole canceled.
    The Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Collection
  - Ten Shillings728 728, 488; Signers: George Wyllys, Benj. Payne
    The hand on the state seal points to the left. Slash canceled.
    EANA mail bid auction 12/01/07 lot 422. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Twenty Shillings6323 6323, 489; Signers: John Chester, J. Hamlin
    The number and first signature are in light red, and the second signature is in dark red. Hole canceled.
    EANA mail bid auction 02/08/03 lot 549. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Connecticut Currency December 1, 1724New London, ConnecticutConnecticutDecember 1, 1724, CT 12/01/24; Timothy Green; Jeremiah Dummer
  An emission of ฃ2,000 in indented legal tender bills of credit authorized by acts in October and November, 1724 for the exchange of worn notes. The first emission of Connecticut notes was issued on July 12, 1709 from plates engraved in Boston by Jeremiah Dummer (an apprentice of John Hull). The plates were used to print an additional emission with a red AR monogram added to the front of the note and then for an emission re-dated May 1713 that was issued in two varieties, one had scrollwork on the top border of the back and the other has a flower pattern. The next issue was the emission of December 1, 1724, which used the face plates as found on the May 1713 emission but included typeset backs. This was the first Connecticut issue to contain printing on the back. Printed in New London by Timothy Green. The front of each note has scrollwork at the top indent, below the engraved text is the seal of the colony with three grape vines with the motto "SUSTINET QUI TRANSTULIT" (What is transplanted survives). Denominations in this issue were: 2s, 2s6d, 3s, 5s, 10s, 20s, 40s and ฃ5.
  - Two Shillings, Six Pence[?]51 [?]51, 41; Lost; Size: indented upper right quarter of the obverse 68 x 53mm.
    An emission of £2,000 in indented legal tender bills of credit authorized by acts in October and November, 1724 for the exchange of worn notes. The first emission of Connecticut notes was issued on July 12, 1709 from plates engraved in Boston by Jeremiah Dummer (an apprentice of John Hull). The plates were used to print an additional emission with a red AR monogram added to the front of the note and then for an emission redated May 1713 that was issued in two varieties, one had scrollwork on the top bordet of the back and the other has a flower pattern. The next issue was the emission of December 1, 1724, which used the face plates as found on the May 1713 emission but included typeset backs. This was the first Connecticut issue to contain printing on the back. Printed in New London by Timothy Green. The front of each note has scrollwork at the top indent, below the engraved text is the seal of the colony with three grape vines with the motto "SUSTINET QUI TRANSTULIT" (What is transplanted survives). Denominations in this issue were: 2s, 2s6d, 3s, 5s, 10s, 20s, 40s and £5.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the R.M. Smythe Chicago Paper Money auction of February 17, 2000, lot 1005.
- Connecticut Currency July 10, 1733ConnecticutJuly 10, 1733, CT 07/10/33; Timothy Green;
  An emission of ฃ30,000 in legal tender bills of credit. The notes were authorized by acts of February, May and October, 1733 to be partly used to exchange for notes from the issue of August 1732, and partly to be used to finance additional mortgage loans (as had been done in the August 1732 issue); finally the remainder of the issue was to be used to pay for public expenses. The issue was redeemable by May 1st of 1741. The front of the notes were engraved by Nathaniel Mors of Boston on two copper plates, while the backs were typeset by Timothy Green, who printed the issue. Notes printed after the October act were distinguished with the word Octo engraved on the face plate of each denomination. The larger plate (10s-ฃ5) was used again in 1735 for another issue, this time adding the date 1735 on the face of each denomination and completely resetting the typed backs. The front of each note displays the main text in a framed border with an image of an animal below. The animal differed on each denomination and was used as an aid by the illiterate. On the bottom left is the seal of the colony with three grape vines with the motto "QUI TRANSTULIT SUSTTINET" (What is transplanted survives). Denominations in this issue were: 2s, 2s6d, 3s, 5s, 10s, 20s, 40s and ฃ5.
  - Three Shillings Fragment, one half of a note [?]44 [?]44, 44; Signers: Nathaniel Stanley, Hezekiah Wyllys, and William Pitkin.; Size: 138 x 51mm (a complete note would be about 100mm wide).
    This is one half of a 3s note. The central text ends with the word Oc<sup>to</sup> added, showing this note is part of the third part of the emission after the act of October. The space to the right of the triangle below the main text is blank, showing this is not one of the later redated 1735 notes (also the typeset back is like the 1733 variety rather than the 1735 issue). The back half of a seated squirrel is seen to the right of the triangle. The full text on the obverse would have read as follows: <Blockquote>THREE CONNECTICUT 3s [serial number] 3s THIS BILL OF THREE Shillings Due from the Colony of Connecticut in New England; tp the Possessor thereof, Shall be in Value equal to MONEY and shall be accordingly accepted by the Treasurer and Receivers Subordinate to him and for any Stock at any Time in the Treasury Hartford, July ther Tenth in the Seventh Year of his MAJESTYS Teign Anno Dom: 1733 By Order of the General Court: Oc<sup>to</sup></Blockquote>I have not seen the full text for the reverse of this denomination, so I cannot reconstruct it as was done for the front (the front is based on a full example of the 1735 issued as pictured in Newman's fourth edition). Extrapolating the reverse from a 5s note the text of the reverse would read as follows: <Blockquote>THIS BILL OF / THREE SHILLINGS DUE FROM / the Colony of Con- / necticut in New / England; to the Possessor thereof / shall be in Value equal to Money / and shall be ac- cordingly accep- /ted by the Trea- surer & Receiv- / ers subordinate to him, and for any / stock at any time in / the Treasury. Hart- / ford, July the 10th, In the / 7th Year of His / Majesty's Reign / A.D. 1733. By Order of the Geberal Court, October.</Blockquote>Lines 6-10 on the back are divided with a typset design in the center.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the R.M. Smythe Chicago Paper Money auction of February 17, 2000, lot 1006.
- Connecticut Currency May 10, 1770New London, ConnecticutConnecticutMay 10, 1770, CT 05/10/70; Timothy Green II;
  An emission of ฃ10,000 in in bills of credit as Treasury Notes payable in lawful money by May 10, 1772 with two and one-half percent interest. Although previous emissions had offered interest at redemption no succeeding emission offered interest until 1780. There had been no currency printed in the colony since the March 8, 1764 emission and that emission was redeemed on March 8, 1768. Printed in New London by Timothy Green II with engraved borders and typeset text. (This Green is the first cousin once removed of Timothy Green Jr., who had printed currency for Connecticut until his death on October 3, 1763). The front of each note shows the seal of the colony with three grape vines and a hand that points to the right on some denominations and to the left on others. The scroll carries the abbreviated motto "QUI TRAN SUST" sometimes lacking the final N or final T (What is transplanted survives). In the border is: "SIGILLUM: COLON: CONNECTICENSIS" (Seal of the Colony of Connecticut). This form of the seal was on every emission from 1755 -1780. The May 1770 emission was signed and numbered in red ink and usually slash or hole canceled upon redemption. Denominations in this issue were: 2s6d, 5s, 10s, 20s and 40s.
  - Five Shillings768 768, 45; Signers: Benjamin Payne, George Wyllys, and John Chester.; Size: 91.5 x 69mm (front border design: 88 x 69mm; back border design: 75 x 68mm).
    The signatures and numbering are in red ink. The hand in the state arms points to the right. There are winged cherub heads on the design on the back of the note. Slash cancel.
    EANA mail bid auction 1/18/97 lot 258. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Connecticut Currency October 10, 1771New London, ConnecticutConnecticutOctober 10, 1771, CT 10/10/71; Timothy Green II;
  An emission of ฃ12,000 in bills of credit as Treasury Notes payable in lawful money by October 10, 1773 without interest. Previous emissions had offered interest at redemption. Printed in New London by Timothy Green II with engraved borders and typeset text. (This Green is the first cousin once removed of Timothy Green Jr., who had printed currency for Connecticut until his death on October 3, 1763). The front of each note shows the seal of the colony with three grape vines and a hand that points to the right on some denominations and to the left on others. The scroll carries the abbreviated motto "QUI TRAN SUST" sometimes lacking the final N or final T (What is transplanted survives). In the border is: "SIGILLUM: COLON: CONNECTICENSIS" (Seal of the Colony of Connecticut). This form of the seal was on every emission from 1755 -1780. The October 1771 emission was signed and numbered in red ink and usually slash or hole canceled upon redemption. Denominations in this issue were: 2s6d, 5s, 10s, 20s and 40s.
  - Five Shillings2067 2067, 46; Signers: William Pitkin, Benjamin Payne and Elisha Williams.; Size: 90 x 72mm (front border design: 87 x 69mm; back border design: 71 x 52mm).
    The signatures and numbering are in faded red ink. The hand in the state arms points to the left. Slash cancel. Also, there is some old collector tape on the back of the note.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 11/1/97, lot 336.
  - Ten Shillings430 430, 481; Signers: Elisha Williams, George Wyllys, William Pitkin
    The signatures and numbering are in red ink. The hand in the state arms points to the left. The note is in two pieces and has been repaired with collector tape on the back of the note. On the reverse there are there is a handwritten annotation that reads "13/4" probably indicating thirteen shillings, four pence.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction of 12/7/02, lot 475.
- Connecticut Currency June 1, 1773New London, ConnecticutConnecticutJune 1, 1773, CT 06/01/73; Timothy Green II;
  An emission of ฃ12,000 in bills of credit as Treasury Notes payable in lawful money by June 1, 1775 without interest. Printed in New London by Timothy Green II with engraved borders and typeset text. (This Green is the first cousin once removed of Timothy Green Jr., who had printed currency for Connecticut until his death on October 3, 1763). The front of each note shows the seal of the colony with three grape vines and a hand that points to the right on some denominations and to the left on others. The scroll carries the abbreviated motto "QUI TRAN SUST" sometimes lacking the final N or final T (What is transplanted survives). In the border is: "SIGILLUM: COLON: CONNECTICENSIS" (Seal of the Colony of Connecticut). This form of the seal was on every emission from 1755 -1780. The June 1773 emission was signed and numbered in red ink and usually slash or hole canceled upon redemption.. The denominations printed were: 2s6d, 5s, 10s, 20s and 40s notes.
  - Ten Shillings819 819, 47; Signers: Elisha Williams, William Pitkin, and George Wyllys; Size: 91 x 70 mm (front border design: 88.5 x 68.5mm; back border design: vertical dimension-77mm, horizontal dimension trimmed in our example.)
    The first signature and numbering are in dark red ink, the other two signatures are in a light red ink. The hand on the seal points to the right. There are winged cherub heads in the reverse border design. Slash cancel.
    EANA mail bid auction 11/16/96 lot 515. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Two Shillings, Six Pence2072 2072, 482; Signers: Benj. Payne, Elisha Williams, Wm. Pitkin
    The first signature is in light red ink and the second signature is in dark red ink. The third signature is faded. The hand on the seal points to the right.
    E Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Five Shillings835 835, 572; Signers: Elisha Williams, Wm. Pitkin, George Wyllys.
    The number and first signature are in dark red ink, while the second and third signatures are in light red. This note has split into two pieces along the middle crease.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Connecticut Currency January 2, 1775New London, ConnecticutConnecticutJanuary 2, 1775, CT 01/02/75; Timothy Green II;
  An emission of ฃ15,000 in bills of credit as Treasury Notes payable in lawful money by January 2, 1777 without interest. Newman lists ฃ12,000 while the resolution states ฃ15,000, (see Charles Hoadly, The Public Records of the Colony of Connecticut, Hartford: Case, Lockwood and Brainard, vol. 14, 1887, pp. 432-433). The emission was printed in New London by Timothy Green II with engraved borders and typeset text. (This Green is the first cousin once removed of Timothy Green Jr., who had printed currency for Connecticut until his death on October 3, 1763). The front of each note shows the seal of the colony with three grape vines and a hand that points to the right on some denominations and to the left on others. The scroll carries the abbreviated motto "QUI TRAN SUST" sometimes lacking the final N or final T (What is transplanted survives). In the border is: "SIGILLUM: COLON: CONNECTICENSIS" (Seal of the Colony of Connecticut). This form of the seal was on every emission from 1755 -1780. The January 1775 emission was signed and numbered in red ink and usually slash or hole canceled upon redemption. The denominations printed were: 2s6d, 5s, 10s, 20s and 40s notes.
  - Two Shillings, Six Pence ??59 ??59, 48; Signers: Thomas Seymour, George Wyllys, Elisha Williams (all faded).; Size: not available.
    Signed and numbered in faded red ink. The hand on the state arms points to the left. Note the use of typographic designs to fill empty spaces, such as design after the date. On the back in red ink is the redemption registration: "Register[e]d J. Jeffery G[eneral] Cl[er]k."
    This note is courtesy of James Conner Poynor, in whose collection it resides.
  - Twenty Shillings358 358, 553; Signers: George Wyllys, Benjamin Payne, Elisha Williams.
    The number and all three signatures are in red. The hand in the state arms points to the right.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment from Stacks The Americana Sale, Jan. 2008.
- Connecticut Currency May 10, 1775New London, ConnecticutConnecticutMay 10, 1775, CT 05/10/75; Timothy Green II;
  An emission of ฃ50,000 in bills of credit as Treasury Notes payable in lawful money by May 10, 1777 without interest. Printed in New London by Timothy Green II with engraved borders and typeset text. (This Green is the first cousin once removed of Timothy Green Jr., who had printed currency for Connecticut until his death on October 3, 1763). The front of each note shows the seal of the colony with three grape vines and a hand that points to the right on some denominations and to the left on others. The scroll carries the abbreviated motto "QUI TRAN SUST" sometimes lacking the final N or final T (What is transplanted survives). In the border is: "SIGILLUM: COLON: CONNECTICENSIS" (Seal of the Colony of Connecticut). This form of the seal was on every emission from 1755 -1780. The May 1775 emission was signed and numbered in red ink and usually slash or hole canceled upon redemption. The denominations printed were: 2s6d, 10s, 20s and 40s notes.
  - Forty Shillings15351 15351, 49; Signers: William Pitkin, Jesse Root, Jabez Hamlin.; Size: 89 x 69 mm (front border design: 88 x 68mm; back border design: 52 x 65mm).
    Signed and numbered in red ink. The hand on the state arms points to the left. Note the use of typographic designs to fill empty spaces, such as the upside down hand to the left of "Forty" at the top of the bill.
    EANA mail bid auction 12/02/95 lot 409. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Connecticut Currency June 1, 1775New London, ConnecticutConnecticutJune 1, 1775, CT 06/01/75; Timothy Green II;
  An emission of ฃ50,000 in bills of credit as Treasury Notes to be redeemed in lawful money by June 1, 1778. Printed in New London by Timothy Green II with engraved borders and typeset text. (This Green is the first cousin once removed of Timothy Green Jr., who had printed currency for Connecticut until his death on October 3, 1763). The front of each note shows the seal of the colony with three grape vines and a hand that points to the right on some denominations and to the left on others. The scroll carries the abbreviated motto "QUI TRAN SUST" sometimes lacking the final N or final T (What is transplanted survives). In the border is: "SIGILLUM: COLON: CONNECTICENSIS" (Seal of the Colony of Connecticut). This form of the seal was on every emission from 1755 -1780. The June 1775 emission was signed and numbered in red ink and usually slash or hole canceled upon redemption. Denominations printed were: 2s6d, 6s, 10s, 20s and 40s.
  - Five Shillings8335 8335, 483; Signers: Elisha Williams, William Pitkin, George Wyllys.
    The number and first signature are in dark red ink, the second and third signatures are in light red ink. The hand on the state arms points to the left. Winged cherub heads on the design on the back of the note.
    Purchased with the Robert H. Gore Numismatic endowment from the John J. Ford Collection (Stacks) October 2006, lot 8001.
  - Twenty Shillings4783 4783, 50; Signers: Jesse Root,Elisha Williams, William Pitkin.; Size: 91 x 72 mm (front border design: 88 x 69mm; back border design: 56 x 68mm).
    Signed and numbered in red ink. The hand on the state arms points to the right. Winged cherub heads on the design on the back of the note. Slash cancel.
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 lot 410. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Forty Shillings10309 10309, 484; Signers: Thomas Seymour, George Wyllys, Benjamin Payne
    Numbered and signed in light red ink. The hand on the state arms points to the right. Handwritten annotations appear on the back which read, "3/4," probably indicating three shillings, four pence.
    EAHA, auction. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore endowment 12/01/07 lot 2025,
- Connecticut Currency July 1, 1775New London, ConnecticutConnecticutJuly 1, 1775, CT 07/01/75; Timothy Green II;
  An emission of ฃ50,000 in in bills of credit as Treasury Notes to be redeemed in lawful money by December 31, 1779. Printed in New London by Timothy Green II with engraved borders and typeset text. (This Green is the first cousin once removed of Timothy Green Jr., who had printed currency for Connecticut until his death on October 3, 1763). The front of each note shows the seal of the colony with three grape vines and a hand that points to the right on some denominations and to the left on others. The scroll carries the abbreviated motto "QUI TRAN SUST" sometimes lacking the final N or final T (What is transplanted survives). In the border is: "SIGILLUM: COLON: CONNECTICENSIS" (Seal of the Colony of Connecticut). This form of the seal was on every emission from 1755 -1780. The July 1775 emission was signed and numbered in red ink and usually slash or hole canceled upon redemption. A two shilling note was added to the emission for the first time since 1746. Denominations printed were: 2s, 2s6d, 6s, 10s, 20s and 40s.
  - Forty Shillings10722 10722, 51; Signers: Elisha Williams, Jabez Hamlin, William Pitkin; Size: 93 x 72 mm (front border design: 88 x 69mm; back border design: 56 x 68mm).
    Signed and numbered in red ink. The hand on the state arms points to the right. Winged cherub heads on the design on the back of the note. Slash cancel. Redemption registration on back signed in red ink, "Register[e]d J. Porter, Compt[roller]."
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 lot 412. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Connecticut Currency June 7, 1776New London, ConnecticutConnecticutJune 7, 1776, CT 06/07/76; Timothy Green II;